All right, I want to see a show of hands:
حسنا،برفع الأيدي
how many of you have unfriended someone on Facebook
كم منكم قد قام بإلغاء صداقة شخص ما على الفيس بوك
because they said something offensive about politics or religion,
لأنه قال شيئاً مزعجاَ متعلقا بالسياسة أو الدين،
childcare, food?
حماية الطفولة أوالطعام؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And how many of you know at least one person that you avoid
و كم منكم يحاول أن يتجاهل شخصاً واحداً على الأقل
because you just don't want to talk to them?
لأنكم ببساطة لا تريدون التحدث إليهم
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
You know, it used to be that in order to have a polite conversation,
كما تعلمون،
we just had to follow the advice of Henry Higgins in "My Fair Lady":
كان علينا فقط اتباع نصيحة هنري هيغنز في "ماي فير ليدي":
Stick to the weather and your health.
وهي التمسك بالحديث عن الطقس والصحة .
But these days, with climate change and anti-vaxxing, those subjects --
ولكن في هذه الأيام، مع تغير المناخ ومكافحة اللقاحات ، تلك الموضوعات --
(Laughter)
(ضحك )
are not safe either.
ليست آمنة أيضاً .
So this world that we live in,
ولذلك فإن هذا العالم الذي نعيش فيه،
this world in which every conversation
هذا العالم الذي كل محادثة فيه
has the potential to devolve into an argument,
لديها القدرة إلى أن تتحول الى جدال ،
where our politicians can't speak to one another
حيث أن السياسين لا يمكنهم التحدث إلى بعضهم البعض
and where even the most trivial of issues
وحيث أنه حتى أتفه القضايا
have someone fighting both passionately for it and against it, it's not normal.
تجد من يقاتل لأجلها أو ضدها بشكل عاطفي ،إنه أمر ليس طبيعيا .
Pew Research did a study of 10,000 American adults,
بيو للأبحاث قامت بدراسة على 10،000 أمريكي بالغ،
and they found that at this moment, we are more polarized,
ووجدوا أنه في هذه اللحظة، نحن أكثر استقطاباً ،
we are more divided,
وأكثر تقسماً ،
than we ever have been in history.
من أي وقت مضى في التاريخ .
We're less likely to compromise,
ومن غير المرجح لدينا الوصول حل وسط ،
which means we're not listening to each other.
وهذا يعني أننا لا نستمع إلى بعضنا البعض ،
And we make decisions about where to live,
ونتخذ قرارات حول أماكن عيشنا ،
who to marry and even who our friends are going to be,
ومن نتزوج ،وحتى من سيكونون أصدقاءنا ،
based on what we already believe.
اعتماداً على ما نؤمن به مسبقا.
Again, that means we're not listening to each other.
مرة أخرى ،هذا يعني أننا لا نستمع إلى بعضنا البعض .
A conversation requires a balance between talking and listening,
المحادثة تتطلب التوارن بين الكلام والاستماع ،
and somewhere along the way, we lost that balance.
وفي مكان ما على طول طريق، هذه المحادثة نفقد هذا التوازن.
Now, part of that is due to technology.
الآن، جزء من ذلك يعود إلى التكنولوجيا.
The smartphones that you all either have in your hands
الهواتف الذكية التي إما أن تكون في أيديكم
or close enough that you could grab them really quickly.
أو قريبة بما فيه الكفاية بحيث يمكن الوصول إليها بسرعة
According to Pew Research,
حسب بحث بيو ريسرش،
about a third of American teenagers send more than a hundred texts a day.
نحو ثلث الأمريكييين يرسلون أكثر من 100 رسالة باليوم.
And many of them, almost most of them, are more likely to text their friends
وكثير منهم، تقريباً معظمهم،هم عرضة أكثر لتبادل الرسائل مع أصدقائهم
than they are to talk to them face to face.
من مشاهدتهم وجهاً لوجه.
There's this great piece in The Atlantic.
هناك مقالة ممتازة في مجلة الاتلانتيك.
It was written by a high school teacher named Paul Barnwell.
وقد كتبت من قبل معلم مدرسة ثانوية يدعى بول بارنويل.
And he gave his kids a communication project.
حيث أنه أعطى أطفاله مشروع اتصال.
He wanted to teach them how to speak on a specific subject without using notes.
وقال إنه يريد أن يعلمهم كيف يتكلمون حول موضوع معين دون استخدام الملاحظات.
And he said this: "I came to realize..."
وقال هذا "لقد أدركت... "
(Laughter)
(ضحك )
"I came to realize that conversational competence
أدركت أن التمكن من المحادثة
might be the single most overlooked skill we fail to teach.
ربما يكون واحدا من أكثر المهارات التي فشلنا في تعليمها.
Kids spend hours each day engaging with ideas and each other through screens,
الأطفال يقضون ساعات كل يوم بالإنخراط مع الأفكار وبعضهم البعض من خلال الشاشات،
but rarely do they have an opportunity
ولكن نادراً ما تكون لديهم فرصة
to hone their interpersonal communications skills.
لصقل مهارات الاتصال الشخصية .
It might sound like a funny question, but we have to ask ourselves:
قد يبدو هذا السؤال مضحكا، ولكن علينا أن نسأل أنفسنا:
Is there any 21st-century skill
هل هناك أي مهارة في القرن ال21
more important than being able to sustain coherent, confident conversation?"
أكثر أهمية من أن تكون قادراً على الحفاظ على محادثة متماسكة وواثقة ؟ "
Now, I make my living talking to people:
الآن، وأنا أتحدث مباشرةً إلى الناس:
Nobel Prize winners, truck drivers,
منهم الحائزون على جائزة نوبل، وسائقو الشاحنات،
billionaires, kindergarten teachers,
مليارديرات، معلمات رياض الأطفال،
heads of state, plumbers.
رؤساء الدول، والسباكين.
I talk to people that I like. I talk to people that I don't like.
أتحدث إلى ناس أحبهم. أتحدث إلى ناس لا أحبهم ،
I talk to some people that I disagree with deeply on a personal level.
أتحدث إلى بعض الناس الذين أختلف معهم بشكل عميق على المستوى الشخصي.
But I still have a great conversation with them.
ولكن لا يزال لدي محادثة عظيمة معهم.
So I'd like to spend the next 10 minutes or so teaching you how to talk
لذلك أود أن أسخر ال10 دقيقة المقبلة لتعليمكم كيف تتحدثون
and how to listen.
وكيف تستمعون .
Many of you have already heard a lot of advice on this,
العديد منكم قد سمع بالفعل الكثير من النصائح في هذا الشأن،
things like look the person in the eye,
أشياء مثل النظر الى عين الشخص أثناء الكلام ،
think of interesting topics to discuss in advance,
التفكير مقدماً في مواضيع مثيرة للاهتمام للمناقشتها ،
look, nod and smile to show that you're paying attention,
النظر وتحريك الرأس والإبتسامة لإظهار أنك منبته للكلام ،
repeat back what you just heard or summarize it.
تكرار ما سمعته لتوك أو تلخيص ذلك.
So I want you to forget all of that.
أريد منكم أن تنسوا كل ذلك.
It is crap.
لأن ذلك حماقة !
(Laughter)
(ضحك )
There is no reason to learn how to show you're paying attention
فلا يوجد سبب لتعلمك لكيفية إظهارك للانتباه
if you are in fact paying attention.
إذا كنت فعلاً منتبهاً .
(Laughter)
(ضحك )
(Applause)
(تصفيق )
Now, I actually use the exact same skills as a professional interviewer
الآن، أنا في الواقع استخدم نفس المهارات في المقابلات المهنية
that I do in regular life.
التي أقوم بها في الحياة العادية .
So, I'm going to teach you how to interview people,
لذا ،سأقوم بتعليمكم بكيفية مقابلة الناس ،
and that's actually going to help you learn how to be better conversationalists.
وهذا في الواقع سيساعدكم على تعلم كيف تصبحون محاورين بشكل أفضل.
Learn to have a conversation
تعلم أن يكون لديك محادثة
without wasting your time, without getting bored,
دون أن تضيع وقتك ودون أن تمل،
and, please God, without offending anybody.
بحق الإله، دون الإساءة إلى أي شخص.
We've all had really great conversations.
كلنا قمنا بمحادثات سابقة مهمة.
We've had them before. We know what it's like.
قمنا بها من قبل،ونحن نعلم كيف كانت تبدو.
The kind of conversation where you walk away feeling engaged and inspired,
نوع المحادثة التي تسرح معها وتشعر بالإلهام ،
or where you feel like you've made a real connection
أو التي تشعرمعها أنك تواصلت بشكل عميق
or you've been perfectly understood.
أو أنه تم فهمك بشكل ممتاز.
There is no reason
لا يوجد هنالك سبب
why most of your interactions can't be like that.
بألا تكون معظم علاقاتك مثل سابقاتها.
So I have 10 basic rules. I'm going to walk you through all of them,
لذا لدي 10 قواعد أساسية سأقوم بشرحها لكم ،
but honestly, if you just choose one of them and master it,
ولكن صدقاً ،إذا اخترتم فقط واحدة منها وطبقتموها،
you'll already enjoy better conversations.
فستتمتعون بمحادثة رائعة .
Number one: Don't multitask.
رقم واحد: لا تقوم بمهام متعددة.
And I don't mean just set down your cell phone
وأنا لا أعني هنا بأن تترك هاتفك المحمول
or your tablet or your car keys or whatever is in your hand.
أو جهازك اللوحي أو مفاتيح سيارتك أو أي شيء آخر في يديك.
I mean, be present.
ولكن ما أعنيه ،كن حاضر الذهن.
Be in that moment.
عش اللحظة.
Don't think about your argument you had with your boss.
لا تفكر بالجدال الذي دار بينك وبين رئيسك في العمل.
Don't think about what you're going to have for dinner.
ولا تفكر بما ستقوم بتناوله على العشاء.
If you want to get out of the conversation,
إذا كنت ترغب في الخروج من المحادثة،
get out of the conversation,
أخرج من المحادثة،
but don't be half in it and half out of it.
لكن لا تكن نصف داخل المحادثة ونصف خارجها !
Number two: Don't pontificate.
تانياً: لا تتشبث برأيك .
If you want to state your opinion
إذا كنت تود طرح رأيك
without any opportunity for response or argument or pushback or growth,
دون إعطاء أي فرصة للرد أو المناقشة ،أوالزيادة والتطوير على فكرتك
write a blog.
قم بكتابة مدونة .
(Laughter)
(ضحك )
Now, there's a really good reason why I don't allow pundits on my show:
الآن، هناك سبب وجيه حقاً لماذا لا أسمح للنقاد بالتواجد ببرنامجي :
Because they're really boring.
لأنهم حقاً مملون .
If they're conservative, they're going to hate Obama and food stamps and abortion.
فلو كانوا محافظين ، سوف تجدهم يكرهون أوباما وطوابع الغذاء والإجهاض.
If they're liberal, they're going to hate
ولو كانوا ليبراليين سوف يكرهون
big banks and oil corporations and Dick Cheney.
البنوك الكبرى وشركات النفط وديك تشيني.
Totally predictable.
يمكنا التنبؤ بذلك تماماً.
And you don't want to be like that.
وأنتم لا تريدون أن تكونوا كذلك
You need to enter every conversation assuming that you have something to learn.
أنتم بحاجة إلى أن تدخلوا كل محادثة على افتراض أن لديكم شيء تودون تعلمه .
The famed therapist M. Scott Peck said
كما قال الطبيب المعالج الشهير سكوت بيك
that true listening requires a setting aside of oneself.
يتطلب الاستماع الصحيح بوضع النفس جانباً.
And sometimes that means setting aside your personal opinion.
وهذا يعني أحياناً إلغاء رأيك الشخصي.
He said that sensing this acceptance,
وقال إن استشعرنا هذا القبول،
the speaker will become less and less vulnerable
سيصبح المتكلم أقل عرضة
and more and more likely to open up the inner recesses
وأكثر احتمالاً لفتح ما بجعبته
of his or her mind to the listener.
وما بداخل عقله للمستمع .
Again, assume that you have something to learn.
مرة أخرى ،لنفترض أنك تريد تعلم شيء.
Bill Nye: "Everyone you will ever meet knows something that you don't."
وكما قال بيل ناي "كل شخص ستقابله يعرف شيئاً لا تعرفه أنت. "
I put it this way:
وأنا صغتها على هذا النحو:
Everybody is an expert in something.
كل شخص خبير بشيء ما .
Number three: Use open-ended questions.
ثالثاً: استخدم الأسئلة المفتوحة.
In this case, take a cue from journalists.
وفي هذه الحالة فإن المرجع هو الصحفيين
Start your questions with who, what, when, where, why or how.
إبدء أسئلتك ب من ماذا، متى، أين، لماذا أو كيف.
If you put in a complicated question, you're going to get a simple answer out.
إذا سألت سؤالا معقدا فانك ستحصل على جواب سهل.
If I ask you, "Were you terrified?"
فلو سألتك، "هل كنت مرعوبا؟"
you're going to respond to the most powerful word in that sentence,
فسستقوم بالرد على أقوى كلمة في الجملة ،
which is "terrified," and the answer is "Yes, I was" or "No, I wasn't."
وهي "مرعوب"، وسيكون الجواب "نعم، كنت" أو "لا، لم أكن."
"Were you angry?" "Yes, I was very angry."
"هل كنت غاضبا؟" "نعم، كنت غاضباً جداً."
Let them describe it. They're the ones that know.
دعهم يصفون ذلك فهم الذين يعرفون .
Try asking them things like, "What was that like?"
حاول أن تسألهم أسئلة مثل "كيف كان ذلك" ؟
"How did that feel?"
"كيف كان شعور ذلك" ؟
Because then they might have to stop for a moment and think about it,
لأنه بعد ذلك قد يضطرون للوقوف لحظة والتفكير في ذلك،
and you're going to get a much more interesting response.
وهكذا ستحصلون على إجابات ممتعة بشكل أكبر .
Number four: Go with the flow.
رابعاً: امش مع التيار .
That means thoughts will come into your mind
وهذا يعني أن الأفكار سوف تأتي لعقلك
and you need to let them go out of your mind.
وما أنت بحاجة إليه هو أن تجعل هذه الأفكار تخرج من دماغك .
We've heard interviews often
لقد سمعت في كثير من الأحيان مقابلات
in which a guest is talking for several minutes
يتحدث فيها الضيوف لعدة دقائق
and then the host comes back in and asks a question
ومن ثم يعود المضيف ويسأل سؤالا
which seems like it comes out of nowhere, or it's already been answered.
يبدوأنه وكأنه آت من العدم أو تمت الإجابة عليه مسبقاً ،
That means the host probably stopped listening two minutes ago
وهذا يعني أن المضيف توقف عن الاستماع لمدة دقيقتين
because he thought of this really clever question,
لأنه فكر بهذا السؤال العبقري،
and he was just bound and determined to say that.
وكان عاقد العزم على قول ذلك.
And we do the exact same thing.
ونحن نقوم بنفس الأسلوب.
We're sitting there having a conversation with someone,
حيث أننا نجلس مع شخص نحادثه ،
and then we remember that time that we met Hugh Jackman in a coffee shop.
وفجأة نتذكر في ذلك اليوم حين قابلنا هوغ جاكمان في المقهى.
(Laughter)
(ضحك )
And we stop listening.
ونتوقف عن الاستماع .
Stories and ideas are going to come to you.
قصص وأفكار سوف تخطر ببالك ،
You need to let them come and let them go.
وأنت بحاجة الى أن تدع هذه الأفكار تذهب و تجيء .
Number five: If you don't know, say that you don't know.
خامساً : إذا كنت لا تعرف، قل أنك لا تعرف .
Now, people on the radio, especially on NPR,
الناس على الردايو وخصوصاً على محطات مثل NPR ،
are much more aware that they're going on the record,
أكثر وعيًا بكثيربأنهم يقومون بالتسجيل ،
and so they're more careful about what they claim to be an expert in
ولذا تجدهم حذرين أكثر بخصوص الأشياء التي يدعون أنهم خبراء فيها
and what they claim to know for sure.
والأشياء التي يدعون أنهم واثقون منها.
Do that. Err on the side of caution.
افعل ذلك بحذر.
Talk should not be cheap.
فالحديث يجب أن لا يكون رخيصاً .
Number six: Don't equate your experience with theirs.
سادساً :لا تقارن خبرتك بخبراتهم.
If they're talking about having lost a family member,
فإذا كانوا يتحدثون عن فقدان أحد أفراد الأسرة،
don't start talking about the time you lost a family member.
لا تتحدث أنت عن الوقت الذي فقدت به أحد من عائلتك ،
If they're talking about the trouble they're having at work,
إذا كانوا يتكلمون عن بعض المشاكل التي يواجهونها في العمل ،
don't tell them about how much you hate your job.
لا تحدثهم عن مدى كرهك لعملك .
It's not the same. It is never the same.
فالموضوع ليس متشابها ،ولن يكون كذلك.
All experiences are individual.
فكل تجربة يمكن أخذها على حدى.
And, more importantly, it is not about you.
والأهم من ذلك أنها ليست عنك.
You don't need to take that moment to prove how amazing you are
فأنت لست بحاجة للتكلم ومحاولة إظهار كم أنت شخص مذهل
or how much you've suffered.
أو كم عانيت في السابق.
Somebody asked Stephen Hawking once what his IQ was, and he said,
سأل شخص ما ستيفن هوكينغ ذات مرة عن معدل ذكائه ، فقال:
"I have no idea. People who brag about their IQs are losers."
"ليس لدي أي فكرة. لأن الناس الذين يتباهون حول معدل ذكائهم هم الفاشلون ".
(Laughter)
(ضحك )
Conversations are not a promotional opportunity.
المحادثات ليست فرصة ترويجية.
Number seven:
سابعاً :
Try not to repeat yourself.
لا تحاول أن تعيد نفسك.
It's condescending, and it's really boring,
لأن في ذلك نوع من تبخيس الذات والملل ،
and we tend to do it a lot.
ونحن نقوم بذلك كثيراً.
Especially in work conversations or in conversations with our kids,
خصوصاً في محادثات العمل أو في المحادثات مع أطفالنا،
we have a point to make,
نريد أن نصل لمعنى معين،
so we just keep rephrasing it over and over.
لذلك نحن فقط نقوم بإعادة صياغة الكلام مراراً .
Don't do that.
فلا تقوموا بذلك .
Number eight: Stay out of the weeds.
ثامناً : ابتعد عن الأعشاب الضارة.
Frankly, people don't care
وما أعنيه بصراحة ، أن الناس لا تكترث
about the years, the names,
بخصوص السنوات والأسماء،
the dates, all those details
التواريخ ،وكل هذه التفاصيل
that you're struggling to come up with in your mind.
والتي تعاني من أجل تذكرها.
They don't care. What they care about is you.
إنهم لا يكترثون لذلك وما يهتمون به هو أنت.
They care about what you're like,
يهتمون بما تحب،
what you have in common.
وما الأشياء المشتركة بينكم.
So forget the details. Leave them out.
لذا ،انس هذه التفاصيل واتركها .
Number nine:
تاسعاً :
This is not the last one, but it is the most important one.
وهذه ليست النقطة الأخيرة ولكن النقطة الأهم.
Listen.
استمعوا.
I cannot tell you how many really important people have said
قد لا أستطيع أن اقول لكم عن عدد الناس الذين قالوا لكم
that listening is perhaps the most, the number one most important skill
بأن الاستماع من الممكن أن يكون المهارة الأهم على الإطلاق
that you could develop.
التي يمكنهم تطويرها.
Buddha said, and I'm paraphrasing,
لقد قال بوذا ،وأنا هنا أصيغ لكم كلامه،
"If your mouth is open, you're not learning."
إذا كان فمك مفتوحاً، فلن تتعلم ".
And Calvin Coolidge said, "No man ever listened his way out of a job."
وقال كالفين كوليدج، "مامن أحد فقد وظيفته بسبب استماعه المفرط."
(Laughter)
(ضحك )
Why do we not listen to each other?
فلماذا لا نسمع بعضنا البع ؟
Number one, we'd rather talk.
أولاً ،نحن نفضل الكلام.
When I'm talking, I'm in control.
فعندما أتكلم أكون تحت السيطرة.
I don't have to hear anything I'm not interested in.
ولست بحاجة لسماع أي شيء لست مهتماً به.
I'm the center of attention.
وبذا أكون مركز الاهتمام.
I can bolster my own identity.
وأستطيع أن أعزز الهوية الخاصة بي.
But there's another reason:
ولكن هنالك سبب آخر:
We get distracted.
وهو أن انتباهنا يتشتت.
The average person talks at about 225 word per minute,
فالشخص بالمتوسط يتحدث ما يقارب 225 كلمة في الدقيقة ،
but we can listen at up to 500 words per minute.
ولكن باستطاعتنا أن نسمع 500 كلمة في الدقيقة ،
So our minds are filling in those other 275 words.
لذا فإن عقولنا تكون مشغولة وممتلئة ب 275 كلمة كتلك.
And look, I know, it takes effort and energy
أنا أعلم أيضاً ،أن ذلك يتطلب طاقة وجهدا
to actually pay attention to someone,
حتى تعير انتباهك لشخص ما،
but if you can't do that, you're not in a conversation.
وإذا لم تستطع القيام بذلك فأنت لا تتحدث فعلياً .
You're just two people shouting out barely related sentences
وإنما أنتما شخصان يصرخان وينطقان بالكاد بعض الجمل
in the same place.
في نفس المكان .
(Laughter)
(ضحك )
You have to listen to one another.
لذاعلينا أن نستمع لبعضنا البعض.
Stephen Covey said it very beautifully.
ستيفن كوفي قالها بشكل جميل.
He said, "Most of us don't listen with the intent to understand.
وقال: "معظمنا لا يستمع بقصد الفهم.
We listen with the intent to reply."
ولكن يستمع بقصد الرد فقط " .
One more rule, number 10, and it's this one: Be brief.
قاعدة أخرى وهي القاعدة العاشرة وهي اختصرالكلام .
[A good conversation is like a miniskirt; short enough to retain interest,
[المحادثة الجيدة مثل التنورة القصيرة. فهي قصيرة بما يكفي لجلب النظر،
but long enough to cover the subject. -- My Sister]
وطويلة بما فيه الكفاية لستر العورة --أختي ]
(Laughter)
(ضحك )
(Applause)
(تصفيق )
All of this boils down to the same basic concept, and it is this one:
كل هذا يتلخص في نفس المفهوم الأساسي، وهو :
Be interested in other people.
كن مهتماً بالآخرين.
You know, I grew up with a very famous grandfather,
كما تعلمون، لقد نشأت مع جد شهير جداً،
and there was kind of a ritual in my home.
وكنت هنالك طقوس معينة في بيتي.
People would come over to talk to my grandparents,
فقد كان الناس يأتون ليتحدثوا مع جدي وجدتي ،
and after they would leave, my mother would come over to us,
وبعد أن يذهبوا ،كانت أمي تأتي إلينا،
and she'd say, "Do you know who that was?
وتقول لنا ،"هل تعرفون من كان ذلك ؟ "
She was the runner-up to Miss America.
لقد كانت الوصيفة لملكة جمال أمريكا.
He was the mayor of Sacramento.
وكان رئيس بلدية سكرامنتو.
She won a Pulitzer Prize. He's a Russian ballet dancer."
لقد فازت بجائزة بوليتزر. إنه راقص بالية روسي مشهور ".
And I kind of grew up assuming
لذلك ترعرعت على هذا الافتراض
everyone has some hidden, amazing thing about them.
بأن كل شخص لديه شيء مميز مخفي عنهم.
And honestly, I think it's what makes me a better host.
وبصراحة ،أعتقد أن هذا ما جعلني أفضل مضيفة.
I keep my mouth shut as often as I possibly can,
وهو أنني أحاول قدر الإمكان أن أبقي فمي مغلقاً ،
I keep my mind open,
وعقلي منفتحاً ،
and I'm always prepared to be amazed,
وأنا دائماً مستعدة لأكون مذهلة ،
and I'm never disappointed.
ولم أصب أبداً بخيبة أمل.
You do the same thing.
وعليكم القيام بنفس الشيء.
Go out, talk to people,
اذهبوا وتحدثوا مع الناس ،
listen to people,
واستمعوا لهم،
and, most importantly, be prepared to be amazed.
والأهم من ذلك كونوا مستعدين لأن تكونوا مندهشين.
Thanks.
شكراً
(Applause)
(تصفيق )